<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>adamburton.com</title>
    <description>Write an awesome description for your new site here. You can edit this line in _config.yml. It will appear in your document head meta (for Google search results) and in your feed.xml site description.
</description>
    <link>http://adamburton.github.io/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://adamburton.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>2016-08-10 22:46:57 +0100</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>2016-08-10 22:46:57 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Climate change is happening</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Actually began writing this about two years ago for a leaflet that I wanted to hand out near where I live in an effort to organise some meetings. It took me so long to write it and one night when I was working on it my house burnt down. I have not been able to concentrate on it since. That was over a year ago. It took me a very long time to write, even though it is very short. I wanted it to be factually correct and I consulted with some climate scientists about it. I think it it quite clear and concise and realised it was just sitting doing nothing on my computer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-climate-change&quot;&gt;What is Climate Change?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Climate change refers to the long-term changes in weather conditions that are being caused by global warming. The main cause of recent warming is an increase in heat-absorbing gases in Earth’s atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the Sun warms Earth’s surface some of the heat radiates back out toward space and as it passes through the atmosphere it is absorbed by so-called greenhouse gases which then provide additional warmth back to the surface. This ‘greenhouse effect’ is a natural phenomenon that keeps Earth’s temperature in balance. Human activity is enhancing the greenhouse effect by releasing greenhouse gases into the atmosphere, in particular carbon dioxide—CO₂.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CO₂ occurs naturally in the environment and, like other greenhouse gases, it is a waste product of the fossil fuels that have powered industrial progress for 250 years. When coal, oil, and natural gas are burned in power stations (or whatever else) CO₂ is released. The more fossil fuels we use the more CO₂ is stored in the atmosphere—causing it to retain more heat and thereby increasing Earth’s surface temperature. This is global warming—it is being caused by humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Greenhouse gases make up a small proportion of the atmosphere—they are measured in parts per million (ppm). During the past 800,000 years atmospheric levels of CO₂ have fluctuated between 170 and 300ppm. Since industrialisation began this has increased to around 400ppm and correspondingly Earth’s average surface temperature has risen by about 0.8ºC. This seemingly small increase has huge consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;what-is-happening&quot;&gt;What is Happening?&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The planet has warmed and as it continues to warm during this century the influence that this has on the climate and therefore all life on Earth will be catastrophic. We might limit the damage if we are able to respond—collectively and quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In different regions of the planet climate change is causing vast loss of life and human migration, species extinction, heat waves, rising sea levels, ocean acidification, melting glaciers and loss of ice cover at the poles, permafrost thawing, loss of water resources, droughts, reduced crop yields, pest outbreaks, coastal and inland flooding, increased rainfall—and all the associated effects on local human populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These problems will worsen and some of them will act as part of a chain reaction that may cause irreversible change to the atmosphere and unthinkable loss of life—for humans and all other species. How we choose to continue living in the world will affect how catastrophic the change will be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;institutional-change&quot;&gt;Institutional Change&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In spite of the relative significance of climate change on the international political agenda, and considering the destructive power of climate change to “radically alter human existence” (to quote Tony Bliar), the response from the political establishment has been limited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To reduce the impact of climate change we need to minimise its causes. For one, almost all remaining fossil fuels must be left in the ground. Such a concept is ‘radically’ at odds with the interests of state and corporate power. Though both continue to make claims about their understanding, responsibilities, and commitment to ‘tackling’ climate change, in reality global carbon dioxide emissions have increased steadily since concerns were first raised at the international level in 1988. Britain’s emissions were increasing until the financial crisis began in 2007 and are now on the rise again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The institutions of government and big business have shown their inherent inability to act in a meaningful way to minimise the causes of climate change. Driven by the objectives of capitalism, they must work towards their own short-term interests: maintain power and maximise profits (anything else is public relations). The mass media, supposedly tasked with educating us about these problems, in fact conforms to the same corporate mentality—representing the interests of the wealthy elites who own and control them.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2016-07-11 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2016/07/11/climate-change-is-happening.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2016/07/11/climate-change-is-happening.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>No nuance in voting</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cross.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cross&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I do not have many conversations with friends and family about politics but I did talk about the EU Referendum a fair bit. I had a long conversation with my mum, and two men on a train asked me if I was in or out and we had a brief chat. Some friends have mentioned that they have been talking with people about it. I think this is really positive and I wonder if the need to talk about it is a consequence of the lack of serious discussion in the mass media.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whenever I heard interviews on BBC Radio 4 about the EU Referendum what stood out to me was that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the debate was between two factions of the Conservative Party and therefore limited to their (right wing) interests&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the Conservative Party’s serious internal divisions were not discussed&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;there was little or no substance, discussion was about how much everyone was lying or scaremongering&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I assume that this is reflected across the spectrum of the national corporate media in the UK.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My feelings about how to vote were not at all clear and I think that, if I were to have proper conversations with people about it, they would feel the same lack of a clear understanding. When I spoke with my mum it seemed to me that, whilst she knew how she wanted to vote, her understanding of the situation was as confused as my own. She said that politicians being interviewed on the news “say nothing” and that it was impossible to make any sense between two politicians arguing. This again highlights the limited debate and lack of serious discussion that is being imposed on our understanding of the situation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend, whose father was Greek, and who has visited Greece several times recently, voted Leave. As I understood it, she wanted to express her contempt for the European Union and felt that if Britain exited then some kind of positive change would be forced upon the EU and, down the line, this would help the people of Greece (and Britain and the rest of Europe). I think she was right to act on her principles but it seems to me that the heartfelt nuance of her argument is lost in the process. Again, given the limits of the debate—which are imposed by the media, which represents establishment interests—the results represent only the opinions of the two factions of the Conservative Party.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This lack of nuance is, I think, an intentional part of the political process. There is almost no popular participation in British representative democracy and when I read a newspaper or watch the news I get the sense that the media would like to keep it that way. We learn about what is going on but we are treated as outsiders to the process. It might seem as though the EU Referendum is a rare opportunity for the electorate to have a say in politics but it is not really much of a say. We are permitted only one word: Leave or Remain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, we are not allowed to express our opinions in a meaningful way and our one word response will be misinterpreted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not vote (my housing situation is a bit weird and I could not be bothered to sort it out in time). I regret that a bit but I am not certain that I would have voted even if I could have—and I am not sure if I would have voted Leave or Remain. Like most people I do not participate in politics and it seems daft to vote but then do nothing to help create what I have voted for (I do not mean to criticise “most people” in that sense—as I have tried to suggest, the system does not encourage or even really allow our participation).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have to go to sleep but I will try to add more to this over the weekend. I want to talk about alternatives, in fact I would rather that solving these problems was the focus of what I am saying but if I do not post this now then I never will. And I feel like that last paragraph is a bit stupid. Never mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/march-poster.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;cross&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2016-06-24 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2016/06/24/no-nuance-in-voting.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2016/06/24/no-nuance-in-voting.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Iraqdeathtoll</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Two thirds of the British public estimate that since the beginning of the US / UK invasion of Iraq in March 2003, not more than 20,000 Iraqis (civilians and combatants) have been killed, according to a June 2013 Comres poll. It is likely, however, that between 600,000 and 1.2 million Iraqis have died as a consequence of the invasion*.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/red-water-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;red water&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This discrepancy in our perception of Britain’s violent actions abroad can perhaps be explained in some part by the role of the establishment mass media in colluding with elite interests. By collusion I mean that those who planned and conducted the invasion of Iraq are concerned to prevent the British public from knowing the effects of their policies and the mass media is owned, therefore controlled, by corporations who, naturally, support those policies which are too in their interests. That is not to say that cabinet ministers and newspaper owners, politicians and journalists, want millions of people to be killed in wars but, rather, that in the process of taking their position in society as leaders, editors, representatives, they seek to justify the rewards - control over resources - that such an invasion brings. They justify it in the same way that, for centuries, European elites have justified their actions (and hundreds of millions of deaths) as unadulterated benevolence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our leaders naturally believe that they should reap these rewards, should control resources, should be leaders, because society cannot function without them. Whilst much has changed in the world during the last 100 years there is little, beyond rhetoric, to suggest that where power concentrates, in corporate media institutions for example, it has decided to cease operating in its own interests.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt; &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The actual death toll from the invasion and “all of the evil” that followed**, should become more widely known - 2% of the British public estimate the more probable figure of 1 million deaths in Iraq. I have been thinking about trying to write an article about it and I thought yesterday that I should document the research process on-line. When I went to begin that today I felt as though I should explain myself in more than a handful of words on Twitter. I had for a moment considered what hashtag to use but this made me feel ill, partly because I feel like the words Iraq, death, and toll, when squeezed together and used repeatedly, over and over, at the end of already squeezed together pieces of information, makes light of what has happened and continues daily in Iraq.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This concern is going to arise throughout whatever I end up writing. Discussion of deaths in Iraq should be presented in the context of life in Iraq so that the need to use numbers (600,000 deaths, 1.2 million deaths, 2.5 million deaths) cannot over-simplify or de-humanise these events. I have not decided yet how to approach this but I was reminded of it the other day when reading Island of Shame by David Vine. He quotes two former US national security officials, Anthony Lake and Roger Morris, who resigned from the Nixon administration to protest the invasion of Cambodia:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We remember, more clearly than we care to, the well carpeted stillness and isolation of those government offices where some of the Pentagon Papers were first written. The efficient staccato of the typewriter, the antiseptic whiteness of nicely margined memoranda, the affable, authoritative and always urbane men who wrote them—all of it is a spiritual as well as geographic world apart from piles of decomposing bodies in a ditch outside Hue or a village bombed in Laos, the burn ward of a children’s hospital in Saigon, or even a cemetery or veteran’s hospital here. It was possible in that isolated atmosphere, and perhaps psychologically necessary, to dull one’s awareness of the direct link between those memoranda and the human sufferings with which they were concerned.”
The Pentagon Papers (2); The Human Reality of Realpolitik - Foreign policy 4, 1971.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe, when publicising the actual number of people killed in Iraq - the figures estimated in surveys, collated from media reports, 1000 deaths represented by a circle in an info-graphic, a note in the sidebar - those people, their lives, become a number, millions of bodies, other things, that never had life to begin with. How can we sharpen our awareness of their suffering as we try to comprehend the scale of it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not really sure, at all, how to go about this. If I ask myself how I would feel about one million British people being killed in similar circumstances, I find myself unable to think anything, blinking, trying to shake the idea out of my head. Is it possible to empathise with so many grieving families? Is it possible to understand the impact that a war has on the individuals and the society when you have never experienced anything like it?
As I learn about the many causes of the many deaths in Iraq, hopefully, I can learn about Iraqi society and find a way to present the lives of those men, women and children as more than a big number.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/red-water-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;red water&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*
Daniel Thornton’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://countingthebodies.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Counting the Bodies&lt;/a&gt; blog provides details and analysis of the poll.&lt;br /&gt;
This &lt;a href=&quot;https://zcomm.org/zblogs/poll-shows-that-uk-public-drastically-under-estimates-iraqi-war-deaths-by-joe-emersberger/&quot;&gt;Joe Emersberger&lt;/a&gt; article has some more details about the poll.&lt;br /&gt;
And this &lt;a href=&quot;http://medialens.org/index.php/alerts/alert-archive/alerts-2013/735-limited-but-persuasive-evidence-syria-sarin-libya-lies.html&quot;&gt;Media Lens&lt;/a&gt; article provides some useful context for the poll.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**
Noam Chomsky makes an important point in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://chomsky.info/20130524/&quot;&gt;recent interview&lt;/a&gt; in response to a question about the death toll in Iraq:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Now there are some principles which maybe we don’t like to think about but they are there and we created them, we established them. Those are the founding principles of modern international law which comes straight out of the Nuremberg Tribunal, and they can’t be repeated too often. The Nuremberg Tribunal which led to the hanging of German war criminals declared that “aggression is the Supreme International Crime differing from other war crimes in that it includes all of the evil that follows,”.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2013-07-02 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2013/07/02/iraqdeathtoll.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2013/07/02/iraqdeathtoll.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>There is something approaching.</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/c-tattoo.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;c tattoo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In many ways I am a great deal further with the Something Else project than I was the last time that I thought about writing about how badly it is going. But in another way - that I think might supersede all of the other ways - I am not printing the paper, I am not handing something out in the street, I am not organising discussions and so I am no further than I was eighteen months ago when I told myself that I had to get on with it. Some things have happened: I am reading a slightly more than ordinary amount of news related to UK foreign policy. I am fascinated by it. I am learning and changing. But I am not printing the paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have tried to remind myself of one thing all of the way through this but it has persistently evaded my thoughts, leading to these moments of concern: the web site is a notebook for notes of the articles that I have read. I post it on-line for the sake of it - to share the notes. It is not the end and it is not of any concern that anyone ought to look at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I first thought about all of this my intention was to get information off of the web because it seems to me that whilst it is on there it has to be sought out. It only represents a threat to the present system if we go looking for it and whilst it might be true that more people are looking for it than in the past there are still people reading terrible corporate newspapers, worthless free-sheets*. Having time to develop the knowledge required for democracy to function remains a privilege.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that a problem with the web is that it offers an easier alternative to the work of organising in our communities. I am far removed from the world of political activism and am in no place to comment on these matters in such a general way but I know from my small personal experience of trying to work towards community organising that the temptation to put all of my energy into making a web site (instead of going out into the world**), because it allows me to sit at home, is almost totally overwhelming. I am struggling now to undo the effects of it. Recently I had the first thought flash through my mind about deciding to give up making the newspaper. I was in a half sleep, sort of, imagining cleaning the cab of a lorry, brightening up the chrome and the blue surface in the sunshine. And someone asked me how the paper is going and I said “No, I gave it up.” It is quite shattering now when I think about it but at the time it was a perfectly casual thought about something in amongst all of the others. It seems as though this feeling has come about, partly, because of the web site. It is a lot of work and it has distracted me from the real work of printing the newspaper. So I am trying to minimise that side of the work, the web site, to see how much of the problem it is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem might have more to do with what motivates me towards the work. I wish that I knew what it is that I have to see or read or think that would help me to realise how important it is that I print the paper. Not for its purpose - its purpose is to soak up cat urine - but important for me to do the work that I want to do. Important for me to work towards organising, democracy, anarchism. It feels like that in the past when I made a decision to work towards something I had an experience or a thought that was significant to me, for whatever reason, and it helped me towards the decision, likely in some fundamental way. It is probable that I attribute these moments to more of the thoughts / decisions than is true but I am confident that it has happened like that on a few occasions. And here I feel as though for me to convince myself that I have to print the paper is going to take some terrible injustice that I have to react against. But I know that every link posted to the web site during the last eighteen months has documented a terrible injustice that ought to move me to action. So I cannot use that as some sort of excuse, it would be pathetic. Whatever it is that will take hold of me and force me to do something exists outside of the work that I am doing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(There is something approaching and it is an important time. I should prepare myself to get the reason for the project in to hands.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/print-room.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;print room&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;*I think there is something to be said for independence in writing, journalism, and publishing. I make a newspaper and that newspaper represents my interests, obviously. It might not be so simple but I think this points stands: if I had the money to make a newspaper with national or global circulation I would have a different set of interests to those I have today and those interests would be in the command of capital, mine and my fellow capitalists and the newspaper would continue to represent my interests. Individual journalists might be able to carve out some form of independence from within a large institution but I do not think that this is enough, it does not justify the terrible things that the institution does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For instance, a couple of days ago I read an article on CagePrisoners about the Somali born, former British citizen Mahdi Hashi who had disappeared earlier this year from Somalia and re-appeared this month in a New York courthouse. Mahdi’s British citizenship has been revoked by the Home Secretary, Theresa May, meaning that the British government is not obliged to question his rendition. Given the last ten or so years of protest that the British government has faced in extraditing British citizens to the United States it seems possible that the revocation of Mahdi’s citizenship was part of a deliberate plot to avoid the extradition process, which is already heavily weighted against the rights of individuals. The article was written by a staff writer at the Daily Mail and had been reproduced on the CagePrisoners web site. My mum reads the Daily Mail and I wish she did not but she might have read that article by that unnamed staff writer and whilst it makes me glad to know that someone is doing good work there it does not make me think that the rest of it is okay, a means to an end, or something. The same goes for The Guardian: the occasional brilliant commentary article does not excuse the destructive consumerism promoted throughout - which is certainly a function of the newspaper.
(See Media Lens for some useful information.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I am generally more interested in what independent journalists, citizen journalists, bloggers, and such, have to say than their corporate-media counterparts and I want the work that I do to encourage movement away from those institutions so that they can be forced to change by popular pressure and so that the value of independent media is better recognised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;**I suppose that ten years ago it would have been acceptable to casually refer to the internet and the world wide web as a different place to the world, a sort of computer game world in which time spent has no effect in reality. It might have been a stupid thing to say but it would not have been totally detached from the experiences of many. Today, most of us will have experienced or witnessed events in the world for which communication via the internet has been an integral part. These events have made the internet a part of the world but I think that the integration is over-emphasised.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a functioning democracy we would have control of our lives, we would govern our own lives, and we would work collectively to organise the infrastructure in a way that supports everyone and represents everyone’s interests and needs. This collectivisation would operate at a local, regional, and global level. At all levels of the infrastructure we would communicate via the internet, obviously, and it is amazing. But I am not convinced that such forms of communication offered by the internet (as presently exist or might come to exist) can replace direct, verbal, visual, whatever, communication between us, particularly at the local level. Media (those things that mediate between us and what is happening in the world: television, newspapers, the web), which represent the interests of established power, actively contribute to the undoing and atomisation of our communities. At the local level, for democracy to function, for community to exist, work has to go on that brings people together in physical communication and whilst I am not saying that everyone who uses the web to put information out into the world is thereby contributing to this atomisation and must be neglecting physical communication I have experienced the way in which the web can distract from that kind of work that I think is just as necessary, if not more so. And so I am keen to make a distinction between the two worlds - on-line (OL) and real-life (RL) - as a way of pointing towards the importance of physical communication, face to face meetings, discussion, reading from paper, and objects and things.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2012-12-30 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2012/12/30/there-is-something-approaching.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2012/12/30/there-is-something-approaching.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>as stupid and ignorant as it is possible for a human being to be</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/silchester-west.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;Silchester West Estate&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In May and June of this year I read some books, pamphlets, articles, and essays about education. In the process I came across, made a note of, and typed up several passages from these writings that seem to, for whatever reason, resonate with me to the extent that I felt an urge to make a note of them, type them up and post them here. Some of these quotations went into a project that I was doing named Latymer Projects education project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I worked with Emily Ballard, Natalie Marr, and Alistair Ashe of Latymer Projects in West London, to organise a series of discussion groups on community education. A lot of the reading, though done with the intention of finding useful texts to be read and talked about during the discussions, helped me in the thinking about what the discussions are for, why I organised them, why they are necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had intended to finish writing and post something about all of this, this, before or during the discussions but I was tired of reading and became distracted. The meetings were poorly attended because my efforts to attract an audience from within the housing estate that Latymer Projects is part of were ill-conceived. This experience and whatever I have learned from it seemed relevant to whatever I was going to write here in this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What follows, then, are some mumbling thoughts that surround some quotes from the reading that I had intended to read and discuss as a group at the meetings. As far as I can tell, from reading it through several times, I do not seem to have made a point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Learning to read and write ought to be an opportunity for men [and women] to know what &lt;strong&gt;speaking the word&lt;/strong&gt; really means: a human act implying reflection and action. As such it is a primordial human right and not the privilege of a few. Speaking the word is not a true act if it is not at the same time associated with the right of self-expression and world-expression, of creating and re-creating, of deciding and choosing and ultimately participating in society’s historical process.&lt;br /&gt;
- Cultural Action for Freedom by Paulo Freire, 1970.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discussion should engender discussion.&lt;br /&gt;
My desire to discuss things comes out of wanting to read things but feeling as though sitting, reading, on my own in the lounge is selfish - not entirely, but a little. It seems likely that other people might like to read whatever I am reading also. If I arrange some space to talk about what we have read it might encourage us to get on with it. It might help us to understand better whatever the writing is about - in terms of, er, a lot of things - the relevance of it to our lives. This is part of the democratic process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The level of education in any society can be gauged by the degree of effective access each of the members has to the facts and tools that - within this society - affect his [or her] life. […] If access to facts and use of tools constitute the two most obvious freedoms needed to provide educational opportunity, the ability to convoke peers to a meeting constitutes the one through which the learning by an individual is translated into political process - and political process, in turn, becomes conscious personal growth.&lt;br /&gt;
- After Deschooling, What?  by Ivan Illich (1973).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I suppose that to ‘convoke peers to a meeting’ might be the default response of anyone attempting to change something in the world, or the world. Discussion constitutes the democratic process whilst developing the individual. The formation of collectively organised institutions that are produced by and produce personal growth.&lt;br /&gt;
Noam Chomsky expressed some thoughts about the development of anarchism in this interview:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Peter Jay: How far does the success of libertarian socialism or anarchism really depend on a fundamental change in the nature of man, both in his motivation, his altruism, and also in his knowledge and sophistication?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Noam Chomsky: I think it not only depends on it but in fact the whole purpose of libertarian socialism is that it will contribute to it. It will contribute to a spiritual transformation - precisely that kind of great transformation in the way humans conceive of themselves and their ability to act, to decide, to create, to produce, to enquire - precisely that spiritual transformation that social thinkers from the left-Marxist traditions, from Luxembourg, say, through anarcho-syndicalists, have always emphasized. So, on the one hand, it requires that spiritual transformation. On the other hand, its purpose is to create institutions which will contribute to that transformation in the nature of work, the nature of creative activity, simply in social bonds among people, and through this interaction of creating institutions which permit new aspects of human nature to flourish. And then the building of still more libertarian institutions to which these liberated human beings can contribute. This is the evolution of socialism as I understand it.&lt;br /&gt;
- The Relevance of Anarcho-syndicalism - interview with Peter Jay, 1976.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whatever the positive attributes to be found in the products of today’s education system might be I doubt that there is any intention, from within those who administer and control the system, to transform human nature in the direction that is described above - elements of which are certainly not exclusively anarchist or socialist. There is an attempt to influence the collective human spirit but, as many of the writers I have been reading make clear, it has little or nothing to do with emancipation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Any system of formal education has serious limitations. It fails to reach the working population; offers no chance for late or multiple entry; ignores the educative influences of home, society, and workplace; tends to produce or perpetuate an elite; encourages conformity rather than healthy dissent; and requires ever increasing expenditure.&lt;br /&gt;
- J. P. Naik, 1974. Quoted in Deschooling Revisited by Ian Lister (1976),&lt;br /&gt;
   the introduction to After Deschooling, What? by Ivan Illich (1973).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The opening up of the education system is sought throughout everything that I have read. ‘Perpetuate’ stands out for me from amongst these words. It makes me think about preservation of the status quo, and conservatism - tradition. In my mind education suggests progression and development. John Dewey broadly describes traditional education as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The subject-matter of education consists of bodies of information and of skills that have been worked out in the past; therefore, the chief business of the school is to transmit them to the new generation. In the past, there have also been developed standards and rules of conduct; moral training consists in forming habits of action in conformity with these rules and standards. Finally, the general pattern of school organization (by which I mean the relations of pupils to one another and to teachers) constitutes the school a kind of institution sharply marked off from other social institutions. Call up in imagination the ordinary schoolroom, its time-schedules, schemes of classification, of examination and promotion, of rules of order, and I think you will grasp what is meant by “pattern of organization.” If you then contrast this scene with what goes on in the family, for example, you will appreciate what is meant by the school being a kind of institution sharply marked off from any other form of social organization.&lt;br /&gt;
The three characteristics just mentioned fix the aims and methods of instruction and discipline. The main purpose or objective is to prepare the young for future responsibilities and for success in life, by means of acquisition of the organized bodies of information and prepared forms of skill which comprehend the material of instruction. Since the subject-matter as well as standards of proper conduct are handed down from the past, the attitude of pupils must, upon the whole, be one of docility, receptivity, and obedience.&lt;br /&gt;
- Experience and Education by John Dewey (1938).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should add: John Dewey stresses (in more and better words than this) that in its opposition to tradition - progressive education must not reject all aspects of the traditional method. His advise was sobering as I vainly imagined the potential outcomes of the discussions before they had begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;[The idea of community education] leads to a different concept of the school. It is no longer an isolated building surrounded by playgrounds and fences. It is instead a community facility, set among the shops and public buildings in the centre of a district. […] The daily lives of the community and its children are inextricably mixed, just as they were for most people all through history.&lt;br /&gt;
- Places for Learning in Talking Schools by Colin Ward (1987).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/not-for.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;not for want of desire&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An important lesson that I took from working on this project was that the assumptions I make about the world, as I sit reading alone, are generally misguided. I find myself imagining these new schools emerging from some project that I am thinking about doing. But they already exist. These facilities that Colin Ward describes - directed at children and adults - can be found all over and they have a similar purpose to those institutions described by Noam Chomsky above. They develop from within communities to, in part, fill the gap left by the lack of participation in the democratic process that people desire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;… the educational system as it is presently organized, is a form of regressive taxation, which tends to disadvantage further the disadvantaged, and to provide relief for those already privileged and better-off.&lt;br /&gt;
- Deschooling Revisited by Ian Lister (1976).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, it is this argument that explains de-schooling. The inequity of the system demands its total transformation. For my own sake, I have tried to explain what deschooling is - as I understand it. The system (in Britain, for instance)  is unequal: some are given no education; many are given a standard education up to secondary level; some of these go on to further education; some of these go on to higher education; and a few go beyond this. This might not be the exact definition of how the elite ruling class is constructed but it is one aspect of it. As we follow the path, upwards, through the system each student receives more and more support from the state: someone who has been educated to degree level has received, in the course of their education, more state subsidy than someone who left school at sixteen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process, by which those at or near the top receive greater benefit from the educational system, is reproduced in the classroom where students who, for whatever reason, do better, by some standard, than their fellow pupils are given more attention by teachers and the school through a class system that divides students according to their apparent abilities. Their class status, as in social class, is also a factor in this, sometimes subtle, sometimes overt.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the surface this might seem to be an argument for tuition fees in higher education but this is no solution. The solution, as far as I understand it from reading a little bit of Ivan Illich’s writing, is that the education system ought to be restructured to provide each person with the same standard and level of education. However, if the system works as described above then it would be financially impossible to educate each and every person up to the level of higher education, and so… deschooling. Less school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think the suggestion is that schooling provides children and young adults with a depth and breadth of knowledge, in such a variety of subjects, that is unnecessary for their personal development - unless they are being developed to become mere tools in a factory. Learning should not, therefore, be restricted but rather adapted to each individual’s desires and requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There is no intrinsic reason why the education that schools are now failing to provide could not be acquired more successfully in the setting of the family, of work and communal activity, in new kinds of libraries and other centers that would provide the means of learning.&lt;br /&gt;
- School: The Sacred Cow in Celebration of Awareness by Ivan Illich (1969-1970)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ali, who lives on the estate, came to several of the meetings and we had good conversations about his experiences of being a teacher and of learning about different forms of education. He expressed a need for a place that young people can go to after school to do their homework because they do not have the space or privacy at home to do it. It would also, he thought, give them somewhere to go instead of hanging around on the street. He also said that ESOL classes - English for Speakers of Other Languages - would be well received by people in the area. A local organisation runs an office that small affinity groups can use for administration tasks and a church nearby holds an after-school homework-club but, Ali said, it is very busy and his children are turned away if it is full.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I posted flyers through doors on the estate and took some to a few local organisations. All of this helped me to realise that, with my project, I had shamefully underestimated the people living in the community who had already done the work that I had hoped to instigate. The community had created the institutions that Ivan Illich, Colin Ward, and Noam Chomsky are talking about and whilst they had not solved everyone’s problems and they might not be as radical and progressive as my imagination naively extends they are part of the structure that supports people in their efforts to organise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I did not talk to Ali about this but; I worry that an after-school homework-club would have to work hard to not restrict young people’s independence in the same way that school does. And whilst I do not particularly look forward to walking past groups of teenagers on the street in case they take the piss out of my hair or something, I would rather that they were outside talking to each other than inside - perpetuating the problems of the present system. I do not think Ali would have disagreed had I said this at the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;There are huge efforts that go into making people, to borrow Adam Smith’s phrase, “as stupid and ignorant as it’s possible for a human being to be.” A lot of the educational system is designed for that, if you think about it, it’s designed for obedience and passivity. From childhood, a lot of it is designed to prevent people from being independent and creative. If you’re independent minded in school, you’re probably going to get in trouble very early on. That’s not the trait that’s being preferred or cultivated …&lt;br /&gt;
- Class Warfare - Interviews with Noam Chomsky by David Barsamian (1995).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am not really sure where I am heading with all of this. I do not think I had intended to come to a conclusion. I am making plans to start an evening-class at a community centre near my studio and a lot of what I have learned from doing all of this reading in preparation for the discussions is helping me to prepare for that. The Latymer Project education project failed in its major aims because of my inability to talk with people - in spite of my desire for discussion. As I posted leaflets about the meetings through about twelve hundred doors on the Silchester West Estate I spoke to three or four people and I did not try to talk about the project at all. For discussion to engender discussion it needs to begin and I hopefully can convince myself of the need for that when I go out posting leaflets for this evening class. I will let you know how it goes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/education-project.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;education project flyer&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This bit of writing could continue on into the night with some internal (and a little bit of external) discussion about whether or not to rely on the old institutions or to work towards creating new ones. I might never get around to writing it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2012-12-04 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2012/12/04/as-stupid-and-ignorant-as.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2012/12/04/as-stupid-and-ignorant-as.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Is it worth spending four hours a day reading the news Something Else?</title>
        <description>&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cliffs-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;foggy cliffs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have been thinking, for almost as long as I have been doing, that the process that I go through to keep the &lt;em&gt;Something Else&lt;/em&gt; blog updated, is arduous and wasteful of my time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To explain briefly, I subscribe to a couple of hundred news feeds that I hope might feed me news about British foreign policy. Each day (not always) I read the hundreds of headlines that are fed in and select the ones that, based on some assessment of the article presented by its headline, might have something to do with British foreign policy. Then, if I have time, I read through some of those articles that I have selected, skimming the ones that are less interesting and reading in full the others. I take relevant clippings from these articles and post the clippings on the blog, with a link to the original article and tags that categorise the blog post in some way. I then tweet the headline of the article with a link to the blog, or the original article. Sometimes it is enjoyable, but in general I am worrying that I have not spent enough time on it - the back-log of articles that I have to read is beyond a thousand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point is that, through this process of research I am expanding my perception of what constitutes actions of the British government in terms of foreign policy, and developing my understanding of those actions and the context for them. With that understanding and using the clippings from the articles I hope to be able to put together (not necessarily write) new articles that answer my own questions about the British government’s actions. I also see the blog as a resource for anyone interested in British foreign policy, as it is, hopefully, well indexed by the tags and so provides a, sort of, database of clippings, far from comprehensive, concerning British foreign policy issues. The twitter feed is, potentially, a useful aggregator for whoever might be interested.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem is that all of this takes up quite a lot of my time and when I began thinking about making a newspaper about British foreign policy several years ago I did not envision myself sat at a computer reading the news for six hours a day (which is what I need to do, not what I do). I want to do some of that, but, and whilst I am quite happy for the progress made by the work that I do to move slowly, I want something more to come from the work that has an ever so slightly more immediate impact, not immediate, but, tangible, or something, I am not sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, thoughts about the aims of the project that I wrote down some time last year have been passing through my mind as I scan the headlines. I wrote:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The newspaper will:  &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;answer simple questions about world events in relation to Britain’s involvement&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;listen to the victims of UK foreign policy&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;support the work of non-corporate media and independent journalists&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;emphasise historical context&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This process, that I have described above, does do these things in a marginal way but certainly not to the degree that I had imagined when I wrote them down. Listening to the victims of UK foreign policy, for one, barely registers, because the sources for articles that I am using, for whatever reason, has not developed in that direction, apart from the few articles that are relevant from Pambazuka News and things from allAfrica. I also end up relying on the Guardian far more than I would like. The Guardian has good reporters who do good work and good investigative journalism but the articles (and journalists) are often marred (Marred?) by their processing through the establishment media and therefore can only, with few exceptions, represent elite interests. Independent media, whilst, of course, potentially suffering from the same effects through aspiration, et cetera, still, I should hope, avoid these problems by way of their nature, as independent, non-corporate, or whatever. I should probably read this through before I post it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is in fact little reason to post this at all. It is, really, an excuse for me to type out the thoughts that I have been having this morning about the newspaper and how it ought to work. I HATE the idea of posting this but I have a feeling that this is what ‘blogging’ is and if I continue to write and then delete the things that I have some peculiar urge to tell people on the internet about I will not have much reason to keep a blog anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think that I need to change direction. Or, at least, see what happens if I start my research from a different place than I have been doing up to this point, because, apart from the fact that I cannot motivate myself to get up early enough in the morning to ‘check the feeds’, something is preventing me from focusing my energies on what I have been doing so far. That is some sort of conclusion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p class=&quot;center&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/assets/cliffs-2.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;foggy cliffs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2012-04-07 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2012/04/07/is-it-worth-spending-four-hours-a-day.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2012/04/07/is-it-worth-spending-four-hours-a-day.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Use your sense...</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Use your sense: look at history, think of obvious things, breakthrough the propaganda images, remember that the institutions are trying to indoctrinate you - keep that in mind - compensate for it. And if you do these things I think you can get as good a sense of the world as anybody has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Noam Chomsky’s response to a question about the social sciences.&lt;br /&gt;
From the Q&amp;amp;A of a lecture given on November 30th 1998 at University of Maryland, College Park Graduate School on the New World Order:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.c-spanvideo.org/program/116018-1&quot;&gt;http://www.c-spanvideo.org/program/116018-1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2011-11-26 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2011/11/26/use-your-sense.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2011/11/26/use-your-sense.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Fox Art Licks Vulpes Vulpes text</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;At some time during the winter of 2010 I wrote some or all of this on my phone when I was walking from Clapton to Kingsland in the evening. It was made for the Vulpes Vulpes contribution to Art Licks printed magazine (issue two).&lt;br /&gt;
For the best part of an hour I have been replacing all of the spaces in the text with spaces that are highlit yellow. For that reason only I am putting this here as a PDF file. Perhaps in another time I will put it here with the spaces highlit yellow using HTML.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 class=&quot;center&quot; id=&quot;pdf-downloadassetsfox-textpdf&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/assets/fox-text.pdf&quot;&gt;PDF download&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2011-09-23 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2011/09/23/fox-art-licks-vulpes-vulpes-text.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2011/09/23/fox-art-licks-vulpes-vulpes-text.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Having meetings</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;In September and October 2011 I will be participating in &lt;a href=&quot;https://decalcomaniaproject.wordpress.com/&quot;&gt;Decalcomania&lt;/a&gt;. The article that I am making for that exhibition, which is based on &lt;em&gt;Damming the Flood&lt;/em&gt; by Peter Hallward, is going to begin being made this week. I wrote out about what I think is going to be in it for a while today - at the swimming pool on Columbiadamm - and it led me on to thinking about something important for other work that I do and that is what this post is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The article is being made and handed out (5,000 copies, perhaps) for a number of reasons. One is to tell people about Haiti. Another is to advertise some meetings about Haiti at the gallery that the exhibition is in. In my writing out about what I think is going to be in the article I had some, a few, things figured out and I feel like I will be ready, tomorrow, to read Damming the Flood again, or at least to make a list of particular topics and to see if they are indexed. When I had got to that point the impending problem presented itself and that is what this post is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Penzance, the town that the exhibition is in, I will spend three or four days handing out copies of the pamphlet that contains the article that I am making. I will begin on a Monday. The meetings will be held on the following Friday and Saturday. There will be four of them. The purpose of the meetings is to see if some of the people who might read the article will want to have a discussion about how we can support people in Haiti. The article will inform these discussions. Damming the Flood is about (amongst other things) Haiti’s, um, post-colonial servitude - to put it simply - and perhaps wrongly. By explaining the recent history of the Haitian peoples’ struggle towards independence from the former-colonial powers and by showing the role that these powers have played in maintaining that dependence - the article will, hopefully, help us all to understand better what we can do to support Haitians. This informed discussion is what this post is about - is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the swimming pool I was trying to think about how to say what it is that is going to be discussed and it occurred to me that there was no reason to do this because that is what the discussion is for and that is when I realised what this post is about.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an attempt to write a press release for the launch of &lt;em&gt;Something Else&lt;/em&gt; it occurred to me that I do not want to do that and that I do not want to work on it at all for the next 30 days. Part of the problem was that I could not explain part of the purpose of the newspaper, which is to, well. I have been unable to explain what has been slipping around in a, sort of, lubricated blood-bath of words and feelings for several years. To put it crudely: I want the paper to encourage people to do something. But this is difficult for me to say for this reason: I do not think that I ought to be telling anyone what to do. It was a good moment when I was thinking about this in the context of the Haiti article and it moved over in my head and into the context of the newspaper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided today that I ought to have meetings, once a fortnight, or once a month, to discuss what has been published in the newspaper. Each of us has to make our own decisions about how we want to support people whose problems we are concerned by. That is what the newspaper is part of. The meetings are the opportunity to work out collectively what would seem to be most effective. Without the meetings the newspaper is simply a few particles within the infinite vacuum of the internal dialogue that each of us has about how the world works / ought to work.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2011-09-05 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2011/09/05/having-meetings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2011/09/05/having-meetings.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The power is real and it is what animates the way forward.</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;For one month I will be preparing an article for the forthcoming Decalcomania exhibition. The article will be based on the book Damming the Flood: Haiti and the Politics of Containment by Peter Hallward. During this month I will be reading two things. One will be Damming the Flood, again. The other will be a selection of articles about Haiti, written by Peter Hallward that have appeared in a variety of journals and which are available on the web. As I make my way through the articles I will be making attempts at writing up my notes for on here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The purpose of the article that I am preparing will be to encourage those who read it to read Damming the Flood. The purpose of my preparing will be to condense in a, hopefully, not too pathetic way what I take to be two of the main themes of the book: i) correcting misrepresentation of popular democratic governance in Haiti and ii) the use of foreign aid by former colonial powers as a tool to prohibit Haiti’s independence. (I will be trying to explain here, sometime, why I think that reading Damming the Flood constitutes a valid and worthwhile form of support for the people of Haiti.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the exhibition I will be handing out copies of the article in PensAnts and holding some meetings to discuss the article and Haiti. The title of the article (and this post) is a quote of Jean-Bertrande Aristide, from an interview with Peter Hallward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is the list of articles:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haiti: One More Shameful UN Betrayal - The Guardian, 23 November 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haiti 2010: Exploiting Disaster - October 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Land that wouldn’t lie: Foreign intervention in Haiti - HaitiAnalysis 29 January 2010. (An abbreviated version of this article first appeared as The Land that Wouldn’t Lie in the New Statesman, 28 January 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Securing Disaster in Haiti - 21 January 2010, Monthly Review Zine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our Role in Haiti’s Plight - The Guardian, 13 January 2010.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A Haitian Boat Disaster - Radical Philosophy 145, September 2007, 53-55.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did He Jump or Was He Pushed? Aristide and the 2004 Coup in Haiti - published in eight instalments in Haïti Liberté, October-November 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aristide and the Violence of Democracy - [review essay on Alex Dupuy, The Prophet and Power: Jean-Bertrand Aristide, the International Community and Haiti (2007)], Haiti Liberté nos. 1-3, July 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One Step at a Time: An Interview with Jean-Bertrand Aristide - London Review of Books 29:4, 22 February 2007. The complete English transcript is available online at Haiti Analysis and in French here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insurgency and Betrayal: An Interview with Guy Philippe - HaitiAnalysis, 23 March 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Option Zero in Haiti - New Left Review 27, 23-47, May 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Haitian Inspiration: Notes on the Bicentenary of Independence - Radical Philosophy 123, 2-7, January 2004.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thank you to Peter Hallward for these links.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>2011-08-19 00:00:00 +0100</pubDate>
        <link>http://adamburton.github.io/2011/08/19/the-power-is-real.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://adamburton.github.io/2011/08/19/the-power-is-real.html</guid>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
